{"tossups": [{"question": "One anti-Vietnam War politician with this surname inspired young voters to cut their hair to show support for his campaign. That man with this surname won the 1968 New Hampshire primary but lost the Democratic nomination. Joseph Welch asked \u201cHave you no sense of decency, sir?\u201d to a politician with this surname, who claimed to have a list of 205 suspect individuals. For the point, name this shared surname of Minnesota Congressman Eugene and anti-Communist Wisconsin Senator Joseph.", "answer": "McCarthy (or Eugene McCarthy; or Joseph McCarthy)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician owned a private fire department that refused to put out fires until this man haggled with the owner to buy the property. This governor of Syria ended the Third Servile War at the Battle of the Silarus River. This man died while attempting to defeat the Parthians at the Battle of Carrhae [KAR-eye], legendarily having gold poured down his throat. For the point, name this wealthy Roman general, a member of the First Triumvirate with Pompey and Julius Caesar.", "answer": "Marcus Licinius <b>Crassus </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A resurgence of this rebellion by the White Wave Bandits led Emperor Xian [shee-ahn] to flee from the imperial capital of Chang\u2019an. Romance of the Three Kingdoms opens with this rebellion, outlining Cao Cao\u2019s path to power. This second century CE peasant revolt led to a weakening of the Imperial authority of Emperor Ling and his government. For the point, name this Han era revolt by Taoist rebels wearing a colored garment.", "answer": "Yellow Turban Rebellion (accept Yellow Scarves Rebellion)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "An early pioneer in this field was the daughter of Lord Byron, Ada Lovelace, who worked on the Analytical Engine with Charles Babbage. Hedy Lamarr\u2019s work in this field was used by the United States Navy during World War Two, and Grace Hopper developed the COBOL language in this field. For the point, name this field of science, in which Margaret Hamilton created on-board flight software for the Apollo 11 mission.", "answer": "Computing (accept answers that indicate connection to computers, computer programming, computer science, etc.)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "Description acceptable: Tom Whittaker, who had his foot amputated after a car accident in 1979, became the first disabled person to achieve this feat in 1998. The first woman to accomplish this feat was Junko Tabei in 1975. Lhakpa Sherpa has accomplished this feat nine times, the most of any woman. Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary were the first people to accomplish, for the point, what feat of mountaineering?", "answer": "Summiting Mount Everest (accept descriptions of climbing to the top of Mount Everest)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this decade, a Madame le Brun portrait of the French Queen \u201cen Chemise\u201d caused an uproar for showing the queen in an informal white dress and straw hat. The \u201cAffair of the Diamond Necklace\u201d contributed to the growing discontent with the French monarchy during this decade. Marie Antoinette was placed under house arrest during, for the point, what decade that saw the storming of the Bastille and the beginning of the French Revolution?", "answer": "<b>1780</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A former slave and ruler of this empire, Sakoura, was killed by Afar zealots while returning from his pilgrimage to Mecca. Another ruler of this empire defeated his Jollof [juh-LOFF] rivals at the Battle of Kirina according to the Epic of Sundiata. This empire ruled by the Keita Dynasty fell prey to the expanding Songhai in the 16th century. For the point, name this West African Empire ruled by mansas like Musa I.", "answer": "<b>Mali</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This thinker posited that \u201cthe problem of the twentieth century is the problem of the color-line\u201d in a work that includes the chapter \u201cOf Our Spiritual Strivings.\u201d This man mapped the Black population of Philadelphia for his book The Philadelphia Negro. This man, who created the term \u201cdouble consciousness,\u201d argued that a \u201ctalented tenth\u201d would lift up African-Americans.  For the point, name this co-founder of the NAACP who authored The Souls of Black Folk.", "answer": "W. E. B. <b>Du Bois</b> [dew-BOYSS] (or William Edward Burghardt Du Bois)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "One of these events was halted indefinitely by the decree Postquam Dei munere after the outbreak of the Franco-Prussian War. The dogma of papal infallibility was reaffirmed at the first of these events called by Pius IX. The Second of these events ended the mandate that the mass needed to be given in \u201cEcclesiastical Latin\u201d and could now be given in vernacular languages. For the point, give the collective name of these two councils held in the world\u2019s smallest country.", "answer": "First and Second <b>Vatican Councils </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The United Kingdom and France invaded this country in Operation Musketeer after signing the secret Sevres Protocol. Future Canadian Prime Minister Lester Pearson won a Nobel Peace Prize for negotiating an end to a crisis in this country, which ended the career of British Prime Minister Anthony Eden. Nikita Khrushchev funded the construction of the Aswan High Dam in this country. For the point, name this country that was expelled from the Arab League in 1979 after President Anwar Sadat signed a peace treaty with Israel.", "answer": "Arab Republic of <b>Egypt</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Although this man\u2019s Smalcald Articles were initially rejected, they made it into the Book of Concord. This leader asserted that the body of Christ was present in the Eucharist at the Marburg Colloquy, putting him at odds with Ulrich Zwingli. Charles V declared this leader heretical at the Diet of Worms, and this leader objected to the selling of indulgences, among other issues he had with the Catholic Church, in his Ninety-five Theses. For the point, name this man, considered the \u201cFather of the Protestant Reformation.\u201d", "answer": "Martin Luther", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Queen Mother of this empire, Ifra Hormizd, had her unborn child coronated after officials put a crown on her stomach. This empire\u2019s founder, Ardashir I, defeated the dominant Parthians at the Battle of Hormozgan. Shapur the Great of this empire seized Roman Armenia and later failed to introduce Zoroastrianism there. For the point, name this longest-reigning Persian dynasty, the last Persian imperial dynasty before the arrival of Islam.", "answer": "<b>Sassanid</b> Empire (accept Sasanian Empire, Empire of Iranians, or Neo-Persian Empire)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, the slave Harry runs Nina Gordon\u2019s southern plantation while another character preaches violent retribution for slavery. Pro-slavery author William Gilmore Simms strongly critiqued this author of Dred: A Tale of the Great Dismal Swamp. Abraham Lincoln called this author \u201cthe little woman who wrote the book that started this great war,\u201d in reference to a novel in which Eliza escapes to Canada by crossing an icy river. The title character is beaten to death by Simon Legree in, for the point, what author\u2019s novel, Uncle Tom\u2019s Cabin?", "answer": "Harriet Beecher <b>Stowe </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "The base of this structure may have been influenced by the Church of the Kathisma, a Byzantine structure on the road to Bethlehem. The dedicatory Kufic script around this structure replaced the name of the Umayyad caliph who ordered it built with the Abbasid caliph who renovated it in the 9th century. Constructed during the Second Fitna on the site of the Second Jewish Temple, for the point, name this structure built over karsted limestone on which Abrahamic religions believe God created the first man.", "answer": "Dome of the Rock (accept Qubbat al-Sakrah, accept Kippat ha-Sela)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "A man with this first name routed opposing forces at the Battle of Vimory while leading Catholic troops. A Duke of Guise [geez] had this first name and was killed during a war named for three people with this name. A man with this name claimed that \u201cParis is well worth a mass\u201d while converting to Catholicism so he could become the first Bourbon king of France. For the point, the fourth ruler with what name gave French Protestants many freedoms in the Edict of Nantes?", "answer": "Henry or Henri (accept Henry of Guise, accept War of the Three Henrys, accept Henry IV)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the First Civil War in this island chain, Germany, the U.S., and the U.K. had a naval standoff but ultimately agreed that Malietoa Laupepa should be reinstated as king. After the Second Civil War, those same three countries signed the Tripartite Convention of 1899, dividing the islands between them. For the point, name these South Pacific islands, the largest part of which is an independent nation with its capital at Apia.", "answer": "Samoan Islands", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist\u2019s painting of Christ holding a crystal ball and pointing upwards was sold for 450 million dollars at a 2017 auction. John the Baptist and Jesus play in front of a craggy landscape in this artist\u2019s Madonna of the Rocks. This painter drew ideal human proportions in his sketch of the \u201cVitruvian Man.\u201d This Renaissance Man also designed a helical wing, a parachute, and other flying devices. For the point, name this painter of two versions of Virgin of the Rocks as well as the Mona Lisa.", "answer": "Leonardo <b>da Vinci</b> (accept Leonardo)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this war, Prince Gaston of Orleans, the Count of Eu, led a massacre of poorly armed citizens in the city of Piribebuy. \u201cI die with my homeland!\u201d were the last words of a dictator who died in this war\u2019s Battle of Cerro Cor \u0301a. This war began with that dictator, Francisco Solano Lopez, and the Brazilian government supporting opposite factions in the Uruguayan Civil War. For the point, name this devastating South American conflict during which Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay battled against Paraguay.", "answer": "War of the Triple Alliance (accept Paraguayan War before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Workers in this industry comprised the \u201cEight Saints,\u201d disenfranchised artisans and laborers who began the Ciompi [CHOMP-ee] Revolt of Florence. Many medieval churches and towns in East Anglia are named for this commodity due to being built by donations from merchants of this good. Ypres [EEP] and Ghent served as continental centers of this textile whose production collapsed in much of the world after the introduction of synthetic fibers. For the point, name this textile fiber sheared from sheep.", "answer": "Wool", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A promise of taking this action by Sim \u0301on Bol \u0301\u0131var after the liberation of Gran Colombia was the condition made for aid from Alexandre P \u0301etion, a former ally of Jean Jacques Dessalines.  Isabel the Redemptress championed the Golden Law of Brazil, leading to this action in 1888. Anastasio Bustamante forced this action on white Texans, who circumvented it by declaring one people group \u201cIndentured Servants for Life.\u201d For the point, name this action established by the 13th Amendment of the U.S. Constitution in 1865.", "answer": "Abolition of Slavery (accept anything that implies ending slavery)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Two answers required. A 2019 revival of one of this duo\u2019s productions saw Ali Stroker become the first wheelchair user to win a Tony Award. Another of this duo\u2019s musicals was adapted into a 1997 film starring Brandy in the title role and Whitney Houston as the Fairy Godmother. The last song that this duo wrote together, \u201cEdelweiss,\u201d is sung as a statement of Austrian pride by the Von Trapp family. For the point, name this songwriting pair, whose hit Broadway musicals include Oklahoma!, Cinderella, and The Sound of Music.", "answer": "Richard <b>Rodgers</b> and Oscar <b>Hammerstein</b> II (accept in either order)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This river, and the Nueces to its north, were the subjects of contesting border claims by two countries which was only definitively resolved after a war in the 1840s. Heavy use of irrigation from this river\u2019s water has led to substantial decreases in its flow west of its Big Bend, a remote section of this river that has seen many illegal crossings. For the point, name this river which since 1848 has marked the eastern part of the boundary between the U.S. and Mexico?", "answer": "Rio Grande", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s namesake economic policy involves \u201cthree arrows\u201d of monetary easing. This head of state allied with the Komeito Party to form a coalition supermajority as leader of the Liberal Democratic Party, or Jiminto. This leader sought to change his country\u2019s US-written Constitution to allow for a standing army, in part to combat aggression from North Korea. For the point, name this longest-serving prime minister of Japan, who resigned due to illness in August, 2020.", "answer": "Abe Shinzo (accept names in either order, prompt on Shinzo)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "According to legend, Gong the Sage invented one of these devices made of jade that he used to trick a local governor into doing his bidding. The Mogao Caves contained the Diamond Sutra, the earliest scroll scholars can definitely say was used making this invention. Song Dynasty emperors sponsored the use of this invention to recreate the \u201cThirteen Classics of Confucius\u201d for the imperial collection. For the point, the moveable type form of what device was invented by Johannes Gutenberg?", "answer": "Printing Press", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Peace of Travendal forced Denmark to exit this conflict and return the lands of the Duke of Holstein-Gottorp. Foreign commander Charles Eug`ene de Croy \u0308 was captured near Lake Peipus at this war\u2019s First Battle of Narva. Czarist forces supported by the Kalmyk Khanate defeated Charles XII at this war\u2019s Battle of Poltava. For the point, name this 18th century war during which Russia, led by Peter the Great, expanded into the Baltic states at Sweden\u2019s expense.", "answer": "<b>Great Northern</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After being accused of defrauding Native Americans, this man beat William Stanbury with a cane. This man won one battle by utilizing two cannons known as the \u201cTwin Sisters.\u201d This governor of Tennessee was deposed as governor of another state after refusing to swear loyalty to the Confederacy. This man, who won in battle against Santa Anna at San Jacinto, was elected to a position over Stephen Austin. For the point, name this first President of the Republic of Texas, the namesake of Texas\u2019s largest city.", "answer": "Samuel <b>Houston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Russian patriots adopted this man\u2019s paraphrase of Matthew 26:52 as a slogan. This man is the title subject of Sergei Eisenstein\u2019s 1938 film depicting an attempted siege by the Teutonic Knights. This man\u2019s battles against the Swedes and Germans led the Soviet Union to name a civilian Order of Merit after him, and, in 1547, the Russian Orthodox Church canonized him. Credited with preserving Russia by befriending Sartaq Khan and subordinating to the Golden Horde, for the point, name this Prince of Novgorod.", "answer": "Alexander <b>Nevsky</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}